Chapter 71.
The Jeroboam Story.
Hand in hand, ship and breeze blew on, but the breeze came faster than the
ship, and soon the Peekquad began to rock.
By and by through the glass, the strangers boats and manned mast heads
proved her a whale ship. But as she was so far too windward and shooting by,
apparently making a passage to some other ground, the Peekquad could not
hope to reach her, so the signal was set to see what response would be made.
Here be it said that like the vessels of military marines, the ships of the
American whale fleet have each a private signal, all which signals being
collected in a book with the names of the respective vessels attached and
every captain provided with it. Thereby the whale commanders are unable to
recognize each other upon the ocean, even at considerable distances, and with
no small facility. The Peekquad signal was at last responded to by these
strangers setting her own, which proved the ship to be the Jeroboam of
Nantucket. Squaring her yards, she bore down, ranged a beam under the Peekquads
Lee, and lowered a boat. It soon drew nigh, but as the side ladder was being
rigged by Starbucks order to accommodate the visiting captain, the stranger in
question waved his hand from the boat's stern in token of that proceeding being
entirely unnecessary.
It turned out that the Jeroboam had a malignant epidemic on board, and that
Mayhew, her captain, was fearful of infecting the Peekquad's company. For
though himself and boats crew remained untainted, and though his ship was half
a rifle shot off, and an incorruptible sea and air rolling and flowing between,
yet conscientiously adhering to the timid quarantine of the land, he
peremperably refused to come into direct contact with the Peekquad.
But this did by no means prevent all communications, preserving an interval
of some few yards between itself and the ship. The Jeroboam's boat, by the
occasional use of its oars, contrived to keep parallel to the Peekquad, as she
heavily forged through the sea. For by this time it blew very fresh, with her
main top sail back, though indeed at times by the sudden onset of a large
rolling wave, the boat would be pushed some way ahead, but would be soon
skillfully brought to her proper bearings again. Subject to this and
other the like interruptions now and then, a conversation was sustained
between the two parties, but at intervals not without still another
interruption of a very different sort.
Pulling an ore in the Jeroboam's boat was a man of singular appearance, even
in that wild whailing life where individual notabilities make up all
totalities. He was a small, short, youngish man, sprinkled all over his
face with freckles and wearing redundant yellow hair. A long skirted
cabalistically cut coat of a faded walnut tinge enveloped him, the
overlapping sleeves of which were rolled up on his wrists. A deep, settled,
fanatic delirium was in his eyes. So soon as this figure had been first
described, Stub had exclaimed, "That's he. That's he." The long tedd scaramoosh
the town hose company told us of. Stub here alluded to a strange story told of
the Jeroboam, and a certain man among her crew sometime previous when the
Peekquad spoke the town hoe. According to this account and what was
subsequently learned, it seemed that the Scaramoosh in question had gained a
wonderful ascendancy over almost everybody in the Jeroboam. His story was this.
He had originally been nurtured among the crazy society of Nesuna Shakers,
where he had been a great prophet in their cracked secret meetings, having
several times descended from heaven by way of a trap door, announcing the
speedy opening of the seventh vial, which he carried in his vest pocket, but
which, instead of containing gunpowder, was supposed to be charged with ludinum.
A strange apostolic whim having seized him, he had left Nesca for Nantucket,
where, with that cunning peculiar to craziness, he assumed a steady common
sense exterior, and offered himself as a greenhand candidate for the Jerobom's
whailing voyage. They engaged him, but straight away upon the ships getting out
of sight of land, his insanity broke out in a fresh. He announced himself as the
Archangel Gabriel and commanded the captain to jump overboard. He published
his manifesto whereby he set himself forth as the deliverer of the aisles of
the sea and vicer general of all oceanica.
the unflinching earnestness with which he declared these things, the dark,
daring play of his sleepless, excited imagination, and all the prednatural
terrors of real delirium, united to invest this Gabriel in the minds of the
majority of the ignorant crew with an atmosphere of sacredness.
Moreover, they were afraid of him, as such a man, however, was not of much
practical use in the ship, especially as he refused to work except when he
pleased, the incredulous captain would fain have been rid of him. But apprised
that that individual's intention was to land him in the first convenient port,
the archangel forthwith opened all his seals and vials, devoting the ship and
all hands to unconditional pdition in case this intention was carried out. So
strongly did he work upon his disciples among the crew that at last in a body
they went to the captain and told him, "If Gabriel was sent from the ship, not
a man of them would remain." He was therefore forced to relinquish his plan.
Nor would they permit Gabriel to be any way maltreated, say, or do what he
would, so that it came to pass that Gabriel had the complete freedom of the
ship. The consequence of all this was that the archangel cared little or
nothing for the captain and mates, and since the epidemic had broken out, he
carried a higher hand than ever, declaring that the plague, as he called
it, was at his sole command, nor should it be stayed, but according to his good
pleasure. The sailors, mostly poor devils, cringed, and some of them fawned
before him in obedience to his instructions, sometimes rendering him
personal homage as to a god. Such things may seem incredible, but however
wondrous they are true, nor is the history of fanatics half so striking in
respect to the measureless selfdeception of the fanatic himself, as his
measureless power of deceiving and bedeviling so many others. But it is
time to return to the Peekquad.
I fear not thy epidemic, man, said Ahab from the bull works to Captain Mayhew,
who stood in the boat stern. Come on board. But now Gabriel started to his
feet. Think, think of the fevers yellow and billious. Beware of the horrible
plague. Gabriel, Gabriel, cried Captain Mayhew. Thou must either. But that
instant a headlong wave shot the boat far ahead, and its seathings drowned all speech.
"Hast thou seen the white whale?"
demanded Ahab, when the boat drifted back. "Think, think of thy whaleboat,
stoven and sunk? Beware of the horrible tale." I tell thee again, Gabriel, that
But again the boat tore ahead as if dragged by fiends. Nothing was said for
some moments, while a succession of riotous waves rolled by, which by one of
those occasional caprices of the seas were tumbling, not heaving it. Meantime
the hoisted sperm whale's head jogged about very violently, and Gabriel was
seen eyeing it with rather more apprehensiveness than his archangel
nature seemed to warrant. When this interlude was over, Captain Mayhew began
a dark story concerning Moby Dick, not however without frequent interruptions
from Gabriel whenever his name was mentioned and the crazy sea that seemed leagued with him.
It seemed that the Jeroboam had not long left home, when upon speaking a whale
ship, her people were reliably apprised of the existence of Moby Dick and the
havoc he had made. Greedily sucking in this intelligence, Gabriel solemnly
warned the captain against attacking the white whale in case the monster should
be seen. In his jibbering insanity, pronouncing the white whale to be no
less a being than the shaker god incarnated, the shakers receiving the
Bible. But when some year or two afterward Moby Dick was fairly cited
from the mast heads, Macy, the chief mate, burned with aror to encounter him,
and the captain himself being not unwilling to let him have the
opportunity, despite all the archangel's denunciations and forewarnings, Macy
succeeded in persuading five men to man his boat. With them he pushed off, and
after much weary pulling and many perilous, unsuccessful onsets, he at
last succeeded in getting one iron fast.
Meantime Gabriel, ascending to the main royal mast head, was tossing one arm in
frantic gestures, and hurling forth prophecies of speedy doom to the
sacriiggious asalance of his divinity.
Now, while Macy the mate, was standing up in his boat's bow, and with all the
reckless energy of his tribe, was venting his wild exclamations upon the
whale, and essaying to get a fair chance for his poised lance. Lo, a broad white
shadow rose from the sea. By its quick fanning motion, temporarily taking the
breath out of the bodies of the oresmen.
Next instant the luckless mate, so full of furious life, was smitten bodily into
the air, and making a long arc in his descent, fell into the sea at a distance
of about 50 yards. Not a chip of the boat was harmed, nor a hair of any
oresman's head, but the mate forever sank.
It is well to parenthesize here that of the fatal accidents in the sperm whale
fishery, this kind is perhaps almost as frequent as any. Sometimes nothing is
injured, but the man who is thus annihilated. Oftener the boat's bow is
knocked off, or the thighboard, in which the headsman stands, is torn from its
place and accompanies the body. But strangest of all is the circumstance
that in more instances than one, when the body has been recovered, not a
single mark of violence is discernible, the man being stark dead.
The whole calamity with the falling form of Macy was plainly described from the
ship, raising a piercing shriek. The vile, the vile, Gabriel called off the
terrorstricken crew from the further hunting of the whale. This terrible
event clothed the archangel with added influence because his credulous
disciples believed that he had specifically forannounced it. Instead of
only making a general prophecy which anyone might have done, and so have
chanced to hit one of many marks in the wide margin aloud, he became a nameless
terror to the ship.
Mayhew having concluded his narration, Ahab put such questions to him that the
stranger captain could not forebeare inquiring whether he intended to hunt
the white whale if opportunity should offer, to which Ahab answered, "I."
Straight away. Then, Gabriel once more started to his feet, glaring upon the
old man, and vehemently exclaimed with downward pointed finger, "Think, think
of the blasphemer dead and down there.
Beware of the blasphemer's end. Ahab stalidly turned aside, then said to
Mayhew, "Captain, I have just beth thought me of my letter bag. There is a
letter for one of thy officers, if I mistake it not. Starbucks, look over the bag."
Every whale ship takes out a goodly number of letters for various ships
whose delivery to the persons to whom they may be addressed depends upon the
mere chance of encountering them in the four oceans. Thus most letters never
reach their mark, and many are only received after attaining an age of 2 or
3 years or more.
Soon Starbucks returned with a letter in his hand. It was sorely tumbled, damp,
and covered with a dull spotted green mold, in consequence of being kept in a
dark locker of the cabin. Of such a letter, death himself might well have been the postboy.
Can't not read it, cried Ahab. Give it me, man. I I It's but a dim scroll.
What's this? As he was studying it out, Starbucks took a long cutting spade pole
and with his knife slightly split the end to insert the letter there, and in
that way hand it to the boat without it coming any closer to the ship.
Meanwhile, Ahab holding the letter muttered, "Mr. Harry Haras, yes, Mr.
Harry, a woman's penny hand. The man's wife, I'll wager. I Mr. Harry Macy ship
Jeroboam. Why, it's Macy, and he's dead.
Poor fellow, poor fellow, and from his wife, sighed Mayhew. But let me have it.
Nay, keepeth thyself, cried Gabriel to Ahab. Thou art soon going that way.
Curses throttle thee, yelled Ahab.
Captain Mayhew, stand by now to receive it. and taking the fatal missive from
Starbucks hands, he caught it in the slit of the pole and reached it over
towards the boat. But as he did so, the oresman expectantly desisted from
rowing. The boat drifted a little towards the ship's stern, so that, as if
by magic, the letter suddenly ranged along with Gabriel's eager hand. He
clutched it in an instant, seized the boat knife, and impaling the letter on
it, sent it thus loaded back into the ship. It fell at Ahab's feet. Then
Gabriel shrieked out to his comrades to give way with their oars, and in that
manner the mutinous boat rapidly shot away from the Peekquad.
As after this interlude these seamemen resumed their work upon the jacket of
the whale, many strange things were hinted in reference to this wild affair.